# 说老北京炸酱面什么特点
What’s the specialty of the Beijing Zhajiangmian?
# 关键在面码 就是一种酱
The importance is the accompaniments, it’s kind of sauce
# 我就爱吃 不但你爱吃
I love it. Yeah I know it well
# 你吃了四十年了 对
You have been eating this dish for 40 years ! Yes !
# 家庭版的 炸酱面
The family version of Zhajiangmian
# 我不知道你还有印象吗
I don’t know if you still remember
# 四十年前我第一次上家去
40 years ago, the first time that I met your family
# 我们现在这老岳母
Your mom, my mother in law now
# 说今儿中午别走了
She said: Stay here for lunch
# 吃个炸酱面吧
Let's have Zhajiangmian together
# 老太太这儿咕嘟咕嘟咕嘟
Your mom cooked the fried sauce
# 咕嘟得有半个多小时
She had been cooking for 30 min
# 酱炸得特别的香
The sauce smelled so good
# 过了一会端上了一桌子面码
A while later, she brought so many accompaniments
# 大盘小盘小碗 十二种面码
There were some big dishes, small dishes, small bowls. 12 accompaniments
# 和好了 还要饧一饧
Finish mixing, put it aside and wait a moment
# 咱拿个小布给它盖上
Cover it with a small towel
# 所以咱们结婚这么多年
So many years that we have been through
# 每次我炸酱的时候
Every time I make the fried sauce
# 一直没断了 老是惦记着
I always remember that
# 五花 肥瘦相间
Pork belly
# 一会煸的时候先煸这肥的
Later I will fry the fat part first
# 今天咱们也得按照标准来 肥的单切
Today we still follow the standard, cut the fat part apart
# 说四十多年 大爷对大妈那么好
40 years! Da Ye has been so nice to Da Ma
# 就是做顿饭吃呗 那不一样
It’s just cooking a meal. No, it’s different
# 那是代表着好多情感
That represents so much love.
# 又出汗了 卖力气 这是力气活
Sweating again! This is a physical work.
# 家里头 是做饭的活儿
In our home, the job to make meals
# 绝对是大爷
definitely belongs to Da Ye.
# 咱看看这叫骰子块是吗 骰子丁
It looks like the dices
# 咱切点小料
Chop something for flavoring
# 搁点姜搁点葱 去掉这肉的腥味
Add some ginger and green onion, to cover the gamey taste
# 葱花切大点 一会儿一煸小了
Chop the green onion a little big. It will get smaller after cooking
# 开始炸酱
Start to make the fried sauce
# 这锅得先烧一烧 热锅凉油
Firstly, heat the pan, hot pan with cold oil
# 先放肥的肉 先放肥肉
Put the fat part first
# 然后再煸出它的油来
Heat it till the grease goes out
# 你看这个油快出来了
Look the grease is coming out
# 但是你看这油不亮
But take a look, the oil is not shiny
# 说明它有水气 肉就容易腥
It means there’s still water inside, the meat will have the gamey taste
# 这油变清亮了 就说明这肉煸透了
Now the oil becomes shiny, it means that the meat is well cooked
# 我准备点虾 以前没见你搁过虾啊
I prepare some shrimps. You didn’t put shrimps before
# 没虾啊 四十年前哪儿有虾啊
There was no shrimps, Nowhere to find shrimps 40 years ago in Beijing
# 那阵儿买肉都买不起 还要肉票呢
Even the meat we couldn’t afford it,  we had to buy with the tickets
# 差不多了 葱姜放进去
Almost done, put the ginger and green onion in
# 酱 我们用北京的黄酱
The paste, this is the yellow soybean paste that we use in Beijing
# 就一般的酱就行 有什么酱使什么酱
In fact the normal paste is fine, you can use any paste that you have
# 要加点水
Add some water
# 酱够咸 咱们不加其它东西了
The sauce is salty enough, so we don’t put other seasoning
# 加点酱油 要它那颜色
Add some soy sauce, to bring the color
# 一是颜色 另外也稀释这个酱
Not only for the color, also for diluting the sauce
# 过去老北京炸酱面咸香
The Zhajiangmian of Beijing was salty and fragrant in the past
# 有的还炸素酱 蘑菇酱鸡蛋酱
There are also vegetarian fried sauce, made with mushroom or eggs
# 这个不能用大火
We shouldn’t use high heat
# 不能大火 小火咕嘟着
Yeah, use the low heat to keep it boiling
# 大妈你看这油多吗
Da Ma take a look there’s too much oil ?
# 看见油了吗 看不出来了吧
You can’t see the oil anymore
# 油都跑酱里头去了
because the oil is going into the sauce
# 待会再搁上半小时以后
A moment later like 30 min
# 看看这油还会渗透出来
The oil will come out
# 着急一点的（炸）二十分钟
If you are in a hurry, boil it for 20 min
# 不着急的话得照着四十分钟（炸）
If you have time, boil it for 40 min
# 多咕嘟会儿 越咕嘟越香
The more it boils, the better it tastes
# 别把它炸得太干了
Don’t boil it too dry anyway
# 你看现在稀稠度合适
Have a look, now achieves its prefect stickiness.
# 什么都不搁 就搁点酱油搁点水
Don’t need other thing, just some soy sauce and water
# 吃酱的原味 吃肉的香味
We can taste the flavor of the yellow bean paste and the meat
# 说老北京炸酱面什么特点
Talking about the specialty of the Zhajiangmian
# 关键在面码和后边的调味
The importance is the accompaniments and the seasoning
# 我觉得这咱们做到了
I think we have made it
# 香气已经出来了 就快好了
The aroma is coming out, it’s almost done
# 大妈给看着点 我再切点葱花
Da Ma you monitor the pan, I chop some green onion
# 再放葱
Put more green onion
# 关火 这就行了
Turn off the heat, done!
# 鸡精 味精 其它调料
Chicken bouillon powder, MSG, and other seasoning
# 什么糖什么都没放
No sugar or anything else
# 我还是就喜欢大爷做的这个炸酱面
I really like Da Ye’s Zhajiangmian
# 够溜的啊 水开了 下面条
Nice, the water is boiling, noodles in
# 煮面水要宽
The noodles must be boiling in a lot of water
# 把酱拿过来 来着
Bring the sauce, here you are
# 这个酱刚才大爷说了
Da Ye said just now
# 慢慢的这油还能浸出来
The oil will slowly come out
# 现在看出来了 大爷捞面
Now we can see the oil, Da Ye takes the noodles out
# 想半天了 过水别过太凉 因为是炸酱面
I have been thinking this for a long time, don’t let it be too cool, because it’s for Zhajiangmian
# 拿碗
Bring the blow
# 吃炸酱面给人挑面的时候要注意
You have to pay attention when you serve the noodles
# 别给挑一大碗面
Don’t put too much noodles
# 你是让人家吃呢是让人家吃呢
Do you want them to eat the noodle or not?
# 还是不让人吃
It is hard to mix (if you put too much noodles)
# 就这么多
Like this is OK
# 放面码也得讲究
And pay attention to the accompaniments
# 颜色（胡萝卜） 黄瓜 豆芽
The color (carrot), cucumber, bean sprout
# 小萝卜 圆白菜 青蒜 绿的
Reddish, napa cabbage, green garlic
# 香椿往中间搁 隆重
Put xiangchun （Chinese Toon) in the middles, gorgeous!
# 芹菜
Chinese celery
# 再搁上酱
Then put the sauce
# 咱该说什么来着
What should we say
# 家有大厨 就是幸福
It’s great to have a chief at home
# shift forward 00:04:51,800
# 有网友问 老北京传统炸酱面的面码都有什么
Some friends want to know, what are the accompaniments for the traditional Beijing Zhajiangmian
# 其实最好吃的大白菜
In fact the best is the cabbage
# 有芹菜 芹菜末
Chinese celery, chop it in small cube
# 有的有扁豆
Some use the hyacinth beans
# 豆芽
Bean sprouts
# 黄瓜
Cucumber
# 冬天的心里美
Chinese roseheart radish
# 这季节呢 还可以搁点香椿
In this season, you can put some xiangchun
# 春天可以搁点香椿
Yeah in sprint we put the xiangchun
# 一半凑够八种面码就够了
Normally 8 accompaniments are enough
# 这八种都是自己喜欢什么就加什么么
So the choice of these 8 accompaniments depends on yourself ?
# 不是
No
# 但是基本有一个定位
But there is a standard
# 你比如说像白菜啊 茄丝 黄瓜丝啊 芹菜啊
For example the cabbage, the sliced eggplant，the sliced cucumber and Chinese celery
# 芹菜切丁
Chop the celery in cube
# 还有青蒜
And green garlic
# 还有青豆
And green peas
# 青豆嘴儿 绿豆嘴儿 黄豆芽
Green peas, green beans，soy sprouts
# 二伯回答问题很全面
Er Bai’s answer is very complete